<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../static/tei_simplePrint.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../static/tei_simplePrint.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
 <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A title</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
           <p/>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
           <p/>
        </sourceDesc>
     </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
 <!--DANI-->
   <body>
      <div>
         <head><roleName>Monſieur</roleName> <persName>Acarete du Biscay's</persName> Journey from <placeName>Buenos Ayres</placeName> to <placeName><country>Peru</country></placeName>.</head>
      </div>
      <div>
         <p>
            <lb/>I Left <placeName>Buenos Ayres</placeName>, and took the Road I 
            <lb/>to <placeName>Cordoua</placeName>, leaving <placeName>Santa Fe</placeName> on my 
            <lb/>right hand, of which place take this ac
            <lb/>count, 'tis a Spaniſh Settlement dependant 
            <lb/>upon <placeName>Buenos Ayres</placeName>, the <roleName>Commander</roleName> is 
            <lb/>no more than a <roleName>Lieutenant</roleName>, and does no
            <lb/>thing but by order from the <roleName>Governor</roleName> 
            <lb/>of <placeName>Buenos Ayres</placeName>. 'Tis a little place con
            <lb/>taining <measure>25 Houſes</measure>, without any Walls, 
            <lb/>Fortifications, or Garriſon, diſtant <measure>80 
            <lb/>Leagues</measure> from <placeName>Buenos Ayres</placeName> Northward, 
            <lb/>Situate upon the <geogName>River de la Plata</geogName>, large 
            <lb/>Veſſels might come up to it, were it not 
            <lb/>for a great bank that obstructs the pas
            <lb/>sage a little above <placeName>Buenos Ayres</placeName>. Ne
            <lb/>vertheleſs 'tis a very advantageous Poſt, 
            <lb/>because 'tis the only passage from <placeName><country>Peru</country></placeName>, 
            <lb/><placeName><country>Chili</country></placeName> and <placeName>Tucuman</placeName> to <placeName><country>Paraguay</country></placeName>, and in a 
            <lb/>manner the Magazine of the Commodi
            <lb/>ties
         </p>
      </div>
      <div><p><lb/>ties drawn from thence, particularly that 
      <lb/>Herb already ſpoken of, which they 
      <lb/>cannot be without in thoſe Provinces. 
      <lb/>The Soil is as good and Fertile here as 
      <lb/>at <placeName>Buenos Ayres</placeName>; and the Town having 
      <lb/>nothing remarkably different from what 
      <lb/>has been observ'd of Buenos Ayres, I 
      <lb/>leave it, and proceed upon my Jour
      <lb/>ney. 'Tis counted 140 Leagues from 
      <lb/>Buenos Ayres to Cordoua, and becauſe 
      <lb/>ſome parts of the Road are uninhabited 
      <lb/>for a long way together; I ſurnished 
      <lb/>my ſelf at my departure with what I 
      <lb/>was inform'd I ſhould ſtand in need 
      <lb/>of; ſo I ſet out having a Savage for my 
      <lb/>Guide, with Three Horſes and Three 
      <lb/>Mules, ſome to carry my Baggage, and 
      <lb/>the reſt to change upon the way when 
      <lb/>that I rid upon was tired. 
<lb/>From Buenos Ayres, to the River Lu
<lb/>can, and even as far as the River Recife, 
<lb/>30 Leagues, I pass’d by several Habita
<lb/>tions and Farms cultivated by the Spani
<lb/>ards, but beyond Recife to the River 
<lb/>Salladillo, I ſaw none. Let it be obſer
<lb/>ved by the way, that theſe Rivers as well 
<lb/>as all the reſt in the Provinces of Buenos 
<lb/>Ayres, Paraguay and Tucuman, that fall 
<lb/>into the River de la Plata are fordable 
<lb/>on Horſe-back; but when the Rains or 
<lb/>any</p>
</div>
<div>
<p><lb/>any other accident ſwells them, a Tra<lb/>veller muſt either ſwim over, or elſe get <lb/>upon a bundle in the nature of a raft, <lb/>which a Savage hawls over to the other <lb/>ſide. I could not Swim, and ſo was <lb/>forc'd to make uſe of this expedient <lb/>twice or thrice when I could not find a <lb/>Ford. The way was this, my Indian <lb/>kill'd a Wild Bull, flead the Hide off, <lb/>ſtuffed it with ſtraw, and ty'd it up in <lb/>a great bundle with thongs of the ſame <lb/>Hide, upon which I plac'd my ſelf with <lb/>my Baggage ; he ſwam over hawling me <lb/>after him by a Cord ty'd to the bundle, <lb/>and then he repaſs'd and ſwam my Horſes <lb/>and Mules over to me.
<lb/>All the Country between the River <lb/>Recife and Salladillo, tho' uninhabited, <lb/>abounds in Cattle and all ſorts of Fruit <lb/>trees, except Walnut and Chesnut-trees; <lb/>there are whole Woods of Nectarine-<lb/>Trees, Three or Four Leagues in compaſs, <lb/>that bear excellent Fruit, which they <lb/>not only eat raw, but bake them, or dry <lb/>them in the Sun, to keep, as we in France <lb/>do Prunes: They ſeldom uſe any other <lb/>than the Wood of this Tree for common <lb/>firing at Buenos Ayres, and thereabouts. <lb/>The Savages that dwell in theſe Parts are <lb/>diſtinguiſh'd into two sorts, those that <lb/>volun-</p>
</div>
<!--GRACIELA-->
<div><p><lb/>voluntarily ſubmit to the Spaniards are 
<lb/>call’d Panpiſtas, the reſt Serranos, both 
<lb/>cloathed with Skins, but the laſt ſet up
<lb/>on the Panpiſtas as their mortal Enemies 
<lb/>wherever they meet with them. All 
<lb/>Fight on Horſe-back, either with Lances 
<lb/>pointed with Iron or Bones ſharpen'd, 
<lb/>or else with Bows and Arrows, they 
<lb/>wear Bulls-hides faſhion'd like a Doublet 
<lb/>without ſleeves, to defend their Bodies. 
<lb/>Their Chiefs that command over them 
<lb/>in War and Peace, are call’d Couracas. 
<lb/>When they take any one of their Ene
<lb/>mies, alive or dead, they meet all toge
<lb/>ther, and after they have reproach'd him, 
<lb/>that either he or his Relations were the 
<lb/>death of their Kindred or Friends, they 
<lb/>cut and tear him into pieces, which they 
<lb/>roaſt a little and eat, making a drinking 
<lb/>Bowl of his Scull. They feed moſtly 
<lb/>upon flesh either raw or dreſs'd, and 
<lb/>particularly Colts fleſh, which they like! 
<lb/>better than Veal. They catch abundance 
<lb/>of Fiſh likewiſe in their Rivers, They 
<lb/>have no ſettled places of aboad, but 
<lb/>ramble up and down, ſeveral Families 
<lb/>together, and live in Tents. 
<lb/>I could not inform my ſelf exactly 
<lb/>what Religion they were of, but I was 
<lb/>told that they look'd upon the Sun and 
<lb/>Moon</p>
</div>
<div><p>
<pb/><lb/>Moon as Deities and as I travell'd along, 
<lb/>I ſaw a Savage upon his knees with his 
<lb/>Face to the Sun, who cry'd out and 
<lb/>made ſtrange geſtures with his Hands 
<lb/>and Arms. I learn'd from the Savage that 
<lb/>accompany'd me, that he was one of 
<lb/>thoſe they call'd Papas, who in the 
<lb/>Morning kneel towards the Sun, and at 
<lb/>Night towards the Moon, to ſupplicate 
<lb/>those fancy'd Divinities to be propitious 
<lb/>to them, to give them fair Weather, and 
<lb/>Victory over their Foes. 
<lb/>They make no great Ceremony in 
<lb/>their Marriages ; but when a Relation 
<lb/>dies, after they have rubb’d his body 
<lb/>with a certain Earth that conſumes all but 
<lb/>the Bones, they preserve them, and carry 
<lb/>as many of them as they can convenient
<lb/>ly about with them in a ſort of Cheſts, 
<lb/>and this they do in token of their af
<lb/>fection to their Kindred ; indeed they 
<lb/>are not wanting in good Offices to them 
<lb/>during their Lives, nor in their Sickneſs 
<lb/>and Death. 
<lb/>Along the <name type="placeGeog">River Salladillo</name>, I took 
<lb/>notice of a great many Parrats, or Pa
<lb/>pagays, as the Spaniards call them, and 
<lb/>certain Birds, call’d Guacamayos, which 
<lb/>are of divers Colours, and twice or thrice 
<lb/>as big as a Parrat. The River it ſelf is 
<lb/>full
</p>
</div>

<!--NICO-->

<div>
   <p>
      <lb/>full of the Fi<reg>s</reg>h, call'd Dorado, which is
      <lb/>very good to eat. There is al<reg>s</reg>o a Crea-
      <lb/>ture in it, whether 'tis Meat or Poy<reg>s</reg>on
      <lb/>no body knows, it has Four Feet and a long Tail like a Lizard.
   </p>
   <p>
      <lb/>From Salladillo quite to Cordoua, you
      <lb/>go along a very fine River, that abounds
      <lb/>with Fi<reg>s</reg>h, which is neither wide
      <lb/>nor deep, for it may be forded over. On
      <lb/>the Bank of it you meet with little Plan-
      <lb/>tations every Three or Four Leagues ;
      <lb/>which are like Country Hou<reg>s</reg>es inhabi-
      <lb/>ted by Spaniards, Portuguese, and the Na-
      <lb/>tives, who have all the nece<reg>s</reg><reg>s</reg>ary acco-
      <lb/>modation<reg>s</reg> of Life they can wi<reg>s</reg>h, and
      <lb/>are very Civil and Charitable to Stran-
      <lb/>gers; their principal Wealth is in Hor-
      <lb/><reg>s</reg>es and Mules, in which they Trade with
      <lb/>the Inhabitants of Peru.
   </p>
   <p>
      <lb/>Cordoua is a Town Situate in a plea<reg>s</reg>ant
      <lb/>and fruitful Plain upon the <reg>s</reg>ide of a
      <lb/>River, bigger and broader than that I
      <lb/>have ju<reg>s</reg>t <reg>s</reg>poken of : 'Tis compos’d of
      <lb/>about 400 Houses, Built like tho<reg>s</reg>e of
      <lb/>Buenos Ayres. It has neither Ditches,
      <lb/>nor Walls, nor Fort for its defence; He
      <lb/>that Commands it is Governor of all the
      <lb/>Provinces of Tucuman, and tho’ it be
      <lb/>the place of his ordinary Residence, yet
      <lb/>he is wont now and then, as he <reg>s</reg>ees oc-
      <lb/>ca<reg>s</reg>ion,
   </p>
</div>

<div>
   <p>
      <lb/>ca<reg>s</reg>ion, to go and pa<reg>s</reg>s <reg>s</reg>ome time at St.
      <lb/>Jago de l’E<reg>s</reg>tro, at St. Miguel de Tucuman,
      <lb/>(which is the Capital City of the Province)
      <lb/>at Salta and at Xuxui. In each of the<reg>s</reg>e
      <lb/>Villages there is a Lieutenant, who has
      <lb/>under him an Alcalde and <reg>s</reg>ome Officers
      <lb/>for the Admini<reg>s</reg>tration of Ju<reg>s</reg>tice. The
      <lb/>Bi<reg>s</reg>hop of Tucuman likewi<reg>s</reg>e u<reg>s</reg>ually re-
      <lb/><reg>s</reg>ides at Cordoua, where the Cathedral
      <lb/>is the only Pari<reg>s</reg>h Church of the whole
      <lb/>Town, but there are divers Convents
      <lb/>of Monks, namely of Dominicans, Recol-
      <lb/>lects, and those of the Order de la Mer-
      <lb/>cy: and one of Nunns. The Jesuits
      <lb/>have a College there, and their Chappel
      <lb/>is the fine<reg>s</reg>t and riche<reg>s</reg>t of all.
   </p>
   <p>
      <lb/>The Inhabitants are Rich in Gold
      <lb/>and Silver, which they get by the Trade
      <lb/>they have for Mules, with which they
      <lb/>furni<reg>s</reg>h Peru and other Parts; which is
      <lb/><reg>s</reg>o con<reg>s</reg>iderable, that they <reg>s</reg>ell about 28
      <lb/>or 30000 of 'em every Year, which they
      <lb/>breed up in their Farms. They usually
      <lb/>keep 'em till they are about Two Years
      <lb/>old, then expose 'em to Sale, and have
      <lb/>about Six Patagons a piece for 'em. The
      <lb/>Merchants that come to buy 'em, carry
      <lb/>'em to St. Jago, to Salta and Xuxui ,
      <lb/>where they leave 'em for Three Years,
      <lb/>till they are well grown and become
      <lb/><reg>s</reg>trong,
   </p>
</div>

<div>
   <p>
      <lb/><reg>s</reg>trong, and afterwards bring 'em to Pe-
      <lb/>ru, where they pre<reg>s</reg>ently have Vent for
      <lb/>'em, becau<reg>s</reg>e there as well as in the re<reg>s</reg>t 
      <lb/>of the Western part of America, the
      <lb/>greate<reg>s</reg>t part of their Carriage is upon
      <lb/>Mules. The People of Cordoua al<reg>s</reg>o
      <lb/>drive a Trade in Cow<reg>s</reg>, which they have
      <lb/>from the Countrey of Buenos Ayres, and
      <lb/>carry to Peru, where without this way
      <lb/>of Sub<reg>s</reg>i<reg>s</reg>tance 'tis certain they would
      <lb/>have much ado to live. This kind of
      <lb/>Traffick makes this Town the mo<reg>s</reg>t con-
      <lb/><reg>s</reg>iderable in the Province of Tucuman,
      <lb/>as well for its Riches and Commodities,
      <lb/>as for the Number of its Inhabitants,
      <lb/>which are counted to be at lea<reg>s</reg>t 5 or
      <lb/>600 Families, be<reg>s</reg>ides Slaves who are
      <lb/>three times the number. But the gene
      <lb/>-rality of 'em of all degrees have no other
      <lb/>Arms but a Sword and Poignard, and
      <lb/>are very indifferent Souldiers, the Air
      <lb/>of the Country, and the Plenty they
      <lb/>enjoy, rendring them Lazy and Cow-
      <lb/>ardly.
   </p>
</div>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>