<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../static/tei_simplePrint.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../static/tei_simplePrint.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
 <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A title</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
           <p/>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
           <p/>
        </sourceDesc>
     </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
 <!--DANI-->
   <body>
      <div>
         <head><name type="personRoleName"><reg>Monsieur</reg></name> <name type="person">Acarete du Biscay's</name> Journey from <name type="place">Buenos Ayres</name> to <name type="country">Peru</name>.</head>
      </div>
      <div>
         <p>
            <lb/>I Left <name type="place">Buenos Ayres</name>, and took the Road 
            <lb/>to <name type="place">Cordoua</name>, leaving <name type="place">Santa Fe</name> on my 
            <lb/>right hand, of which place take this ac-
            <lb/>count, <choice><sic>'tis</sic><corr>this</corr></choice> a <reg>Spanish</reg> Settlement dependant 
            <lb/>upon <name type="place">Buenos Ayres</name>, the <name type="personRoleName">Commander</name> is 
            <lb/>no more than a <name type="personRoleName">Lieutenant</name>, and does no-
            <lb/>thing but by order from the <name type="personRoleName">Governor</name> 
            <lb/>of <name type="place">Buenos Ayres</name>. <choice><sic>'Tis</sic><corr>this</corr></choice> a little place con-
            <lb/>taining <measure>25 <reg>Houses</reg></measure>, without any Walls, 
            <lb/>Fortifications, or <reg>Garrison</reg>, <reg>distant</reg> <measure>80 
            <lb/>Leagues</measure> from <name type="place">Buenos Ayres</name> Northward, 
            <lb/>Situate upon the <name type="placeGeog">River de la Plata</name>, large 
            <lb/><reg>Vessels</reg> might come up to it, were it not 
            <lb/>for a great bank that <reg>obstructs</reg> the pas-
            <lb/>sage a little above <name type="place">Buenos Ayres</name>. <reg>Ne-
            <lb/>vertheless</reg> <choice><sic>'tis</sic><corr>this</corr></choice> a very advantageous <reg>Post</reg>, 
            <lb/>because <choice><sic>'tis</sic><corr>this</corr></choice> the only passage from <name type="country">Peru</name>, 
            <lb/><name type="country">Chili</name> and <name type="place">Tucuman</name> to <name type="country">Paraguay</name>, and in a 
            <lb/>manner the Magazine of the Commodi-
            <lb/>ties
         </p>
      </div>
      <div>
      <p>
      <lb/>ties drawn from thence, particularly that 
      <lb/>Herb already <reg>spoken</reg> of, which they 
      <lb/>cannot be without in <reg>those</reg> Provinces. 
      <lb/>The Soil is as good and Fertile here as 
      <lb/>at <name type="place">Buenos Ayres</name>; and the Town having 
      <lb/>nothing remarkably different from what 
      <lb/>has been <choice><sic>observ'd</sic><corr>observed</corr></choice> of <name type="place">Buenos Ayres</name>, I 
      <lb/>leave it, and proceed upon my Jour-
      <lb/>ney. <choice><sic>'Tis</sic><corr>this</corr></choice> counted <measure>140 Leagues</measure> from 
      <lb/><name type="place">Buenos Ayres</name> to <name type="place">Cordoua</name>, and <reg>because</reg> 
      <lb/><reg>some</reg> parts of the Road are uninhabited 
      <lb/>for a long way together; I <reg>furnished</reg> 
      <lb/>my <reg>self</reg> at my departure with what I 
      <lb/>was <choice><sic>inform'd</sic><corr>informed</corr></choice> I <reg>should</reg> <reg>stand</reg> in need 
      <lb/>of; <reg>so</reg> I <reg>set</reg> out having a <rs type="native_group" subtype="colonial_denomination">Savage</rs> for my 
      <lb/><name type="personRoleName">Guide</name>, with Three <reg>Horses</reg> and Three 
      <lb/>Mules, <reg>some</reg> to carry my Baggage, and 
      <lb/>the <reg>rest</reg> to change upon the way when 
      <lb/>that I rid upon was tired.</p> 
<p>
<lb/>From <name type="place">Buenos Ayres</name>, to the <name type="placeGeog">River Lu
<lb/>can</name>, and even as far as the <name type="placeGeog">River Recife</name>, 
<lb/><measure>30 Leagues</measure>, I <choice><sic>pass’d</sic><corr>passed</corr></choice> by several Habita
<lb/>tions and Farms cultivated by the Spani
<lb/>ards, but beyond <name type="place">Recife</name> to the <name type="placeGeog">River 
<lb/>Salladillo</name>, I <reg>saw</reg> none. Let it be <reg>obser-
<lb/>ved</reg> by the way, that <reg>these</reg> Rivers as well 
<lb/>as all the <reg>rest</reg> in the Provinces of <name type="place">Buenos 
<lb/>Ayres</name>, <name type="country">Paraguay</name> and <name type="place">Tucuman</name>, that fall 
<lb/>into the <name type="placeGeog">River de la Plata</name> are fordable 
<lb/>on <reg>Horse</reg>-back; but when the Rains or 
<lb/>any
</p>
</div>
<div>
<p><lb/>any other accident <reg>swells</reg> them, a Tra-
<lb/>veller <reg>must</reg> either <reg>swim</reg> over, or <reg>else</reg> get 
<lb/>upon a bundle in the nature of a raft, 
<lb/>which a <rs type="native_group" subtype="colonial_denomination">Savage</rs> hawls over to the other 
<lb/><reg>side</reg>. I could not Swim, and <reg>so</reg> was 
<lb/><choice><sic>forc'd</sic><corr>forced</corr></choice> to make <reg>use</reg> of this expedient 
<lb/>twice or thrice when I could not find a 
<lb/>Ford. The way was this, my <rs type="native_group" subtype="colonial_denomination">Indian</rs> 
<lb/><choice><sic>kill'd</sic><corr>killed</corr></choice> a Wild Bull, flead the Hide off, 
<lb/><reg>stuffed</reg> it with <reg>straw</reg>, and <choice><sic>ty'd</sic><corr>tied</corr></choice> it up in 
<lb/>a great bundle with thongs of the <reg>same</reg> 
<lb/>Hide, upon which I <choice><sic>plac'd</sic><corr>placed</corr></choice> my <reg>self</reg> with 
<lb/>my Baggage ; he <reg>swam</reg> over hawling me 
<lb/>after him by a Cord <choice><sic>ty'd</sic><corr>tied</corr></choice> to the bundle, 
<lb/>and then he <reg><choice><sic>repass'd</sic><corr>repassed</corr></choice></reg> and <reg>swam</reg> my <reg>Horses</reg> 
<lb/>and Mules over to me.
<lb/>All the Country between the <name type="placeGeog">River 
<lb/>Recife</name> and <name type="placeGeog">Salladillo</name>, <choice><sic>tho'</sic><corr>though</corr></choice> uninhabited, 
<lb/>abounds in Cattle and all <reg>sorts</reg> of Fruit 
<lb/>trees, except Walnut and Chesnut-trees; 
<lb/>there are whole Woods of Nectarine-
<lb/>Trees, <measure>Three or Four Leagues</measure> in <reg>compass</reg>, 
<lb/>that bear excellent Fruit, which they 
<lb/>not only eat raw, but bake them, or dry 
<lb/>them in the Sun, to keep, as we in <name type="country">France</name> 
<lb/>do Prunes: They <reg>seldom</reg> <reg>use</reg> any other 
<lb/>than the Wood of this Tree for common 
<lb/>firing at <name type="place">Buenos Ayres</name>, and thereabouts. 
<lb/>The <rs type="native_group" subtype="colonial_denomination">Savages</rs> that dwell in <reg>these</reg> Parts are 
<lb/><reg>distinguish'd</reg> into two sorts, those that 
<lb/>volun-</p>
</div>
<!--GRACIELA-->
<div><p><lb/>voluntarily ſubmit to the Spaniards are <lb/>call’d Panpiſtas, the reſt Serranos, both <lb/>cloathed with Skins, but the laſt ſet up <lb/>on the Panpiſtas as their mortal Enemies <lb/>wherever they meet with them. All <lb/>Fight on Horſe-back, either with Lances <lb/>pointed with Iron or Bones ſharpen'd, <lb/>or else with Bows and Arrows, they <lb/>wear Bulls-hides faſhion'd like a Doublet <lb/>without ſleeves, to defend their Bodies. <lb/>Their Chiefs that command over them <lb/>in War and Peace, are call’d Couracas. <lb/>When they take any one of their Ene<lb/>mies, alive or dead, they meet all toge<lb/>ther, and after they have reproach'd him, <lb/>that either he or his Relations were the <lb/>death of their Kindred or Friends, they <lb/>cut and tear him into pieces, which they <lb/>roaſt a little and eat, making a drinking <lb/>Bowl of his Scull. They feed moſtly <lb/>upon flesh either raw or dreſs'd, and <lb/>particularly Colts fleſh, which they like! <lb/>better than Veal. They catch abundance <lb/>of Fiſh likewiſe in their Rivers, They <lb/>have no ſettled places of aboad, but <lb/>ramble up and down, ſeveral Families <lb/>together, and live in Tents. 
<lb/>I could not inform my ſelf exactly <lb/>what Religion they were of, but I was <lb/>told that they look'd upon the Sun and <lb/>Moon</p>
</div>
<div><p>Moon as Deities and as I travell'd along, I ſaw a Savage upon his knees with his Face to the Sun, who cry'd out and made ſtrange geſtures with his Hands and Arms. I learn'd from the Savage that accompany'd me, that he was one of thoſe they call'd Papas, who in the Morning kneel towards the Sun, and at Night towards the Moon, to ſupplicate those fancy'd Divinities to be propitious to them, to give them fair Weather, and Victory over their Foes. 
They make no great Ceremony in their Marriages ; but when a Relation dies, after they have rubb’d his body with a certain Earth that conſumes all but the Bones, they preserve them, and carry as many of them as they can conveniently about with them in a ſort of Cheſts, and this they do in token of their affection to their Kindred ; indeed they are not wanting in good Offices to them during their Lives, nor in their Sickneſs and Death. 
Along the River Salladillo, I took notice of a great many Parrats, or Papagays, as the Spaniards call them, and certain Birds, call’d Guacamayos, which are of divers Colours, and twice or thrice as big as a Parrat. The River it ſelf is full
</p>
</div>

<!--NICO-->

<div>
   <p>
      <lb/>full of the Fi<reg>s</reg>h, call'd Dorado, which is
      <lb/>very good to eat. There is al<reg>s</reg>o a Crea-
      <lb/>ture in it, whether 'tis Meat or Poy<reg>s</reg>on
      <lb/>no body knows, it has Four Feet and a long Tail like a Lizard.
   </p>
   <p>
      <lb/>From Salladillo quite to Cordoua, you
      <lb/>go along a very fine River, that abounds
      <lb/>with Fi<reg>s</reg>h, which is neither wide
      <lb/>nor deep, for it may be forded over. On
      <lb/>the Bank of it you meet with little Plan-
      <lb/>tations every Three or Four Leagues ;
      <lb/>which are like Country Hou<reg>s</reg>es inhabi-
      <lb/>ted by Spaniards, Portuguese, and the Na-
      <lb/>tives, who have all the nece<reg>s</reg><reg>s</reg>ary acco-
      <lb/>modation<reg>s</reg> of Life they can wi<reg>s</reg>h, and
      <lb/>are very Civil and Charitable to Stran-
      <lb/>gers; their principal Wealth is in Hor-
      <lb/><reg>s</reg>es and Mules, in which they Trade with
      <lb/>the Inhabitants of Peru.
   </p>
   <p>
      <lb/>Cordoua is a Town Situate in a plea<reg>s</reg>ant
      <lb/>and fruitful Plain upon the <reg>s</reg>ide of a
      <lb/>River, bigger and broader than that I
      <lb/>have ju<reg>s</reg>t <reg>s</reg>poken of : 'Tis compos’d of
      <lb/>about 400 Houses, Built like tho<reg>s</reg>e of
      <lb/>Buenos Ayres. It has neither Ditches,
      <lb/>nor Walls, nor Fort for its defence; He
      <lb/>that Commands it is Governor of all the
      <lb/>Provinces of Tucuman, and tho’ it be
      <lb/>the place of his ordinary Residence, yet
      <lb/>he is wont now and then, as he <reg>s</reg>ees oc-
      <lb/>ca<reg>s</reg>ion,
   </p>
</div>

<div>
   <p>
      <lb/>ca<reg>s</reg>ion, to go and pa<reg>s</reg>s <reg>s</reg>ome time at St.
      <lb/>Jago de l’E<reg>s</reg>tro, at St. Miguel de Tucuman,
      <lb/>(which is the Capital City of the Province)
      <lb/>at Salta and at Xuxui. In each of the<reg>s</reg>e
      <lb/>Villages there is a Lieutenant, who has
      <lb/>under him an Alcalde and <reg>s</reg>ome Officers
      <lb/>for the Admini<reg>s</reg>tration of Ju<reg>s</reg>tice. The
      <lb/>Bi<reg>s</reg>hop of Tucuman likewi<reg>s</reg>e u<reg>s</reg>ually re-
      <lb/><reg>s</reg>ides at Cordoua, where the Cathedral
      <lb/>is the only Pari<reg>s</reg>h Church of the whole
      <lb/>Town, but there are divers Convents
      <lb/>of Monks, namely of Dominicans, Recol-
      <lb/>lects, and those of the Order de la Mer-
      <lb/>cy: and one of Nunns. The Jesuits
      <lb/>have a College there, and their Chappel
      <lb/>is the fine<reg>s</reg>t and riche<reg>s</reg>t of all.
   </p>
   <p>
      <lb/>The Inhabitants are Rich in Gold
      <lb/>and Silver, which they get by the Trade
      <lb/>they have for Mules, with which they
      <lb/>furni<reg>s</reg>h Peru and other Parts; which is
      <lb/><reg>s</reg>o con<reg>s</reg>iderable, that they <reg>s</reg>ell about 28
      <lb/>or 30000 of 'em every Year, which they
      <lb/>breed up in their Farms. They usually
      <lb/>keep 'em till they are about Two Years
      <lb/>old, then expose 'em to Sale, and have
      <lb/>about Six Patagons a piece for 'em. The
      <lb/>Merchants that come to buy 'em, carry
      <lb/>'em to St. Jago, to Salta and Xuxui ,
      <lb/>where they leave 'em for Three Years,
      <lb/>till they are well grown and become
      <lb/><reg>s</reg>trong,
   </p>
</div>

<div>
   <p>
      <lb/><reg>s</reg>trong, and afterwards bring 'em to Pe-
      <lb/>ru, where they pre<reg>s</reg>ently have Vent for
      <lb/>'em, becau<reg>s</reg>e there as well as in the re<reg>s</reg>t 
      <lb/>of the Western part of America, the
      <lb/>greate<reg>s</reg>t part of their Carriage is upon
      <lb/>Mules. The People of Cordoua al<reg>s</reg>o
      <lb/>drive a Trade in Cow<reg>s</reg>, which they have
      <lb/>from the Countrey of Buenos Ayres, and
      <lb/>carry to Peru, where without this way
      <lb/>of Sub<reg>s</reg>i<reg>s</reg>tance 'tis certain they would
      <lb/>have much ado to live. This kind of
      <lb/>Traffick makes this Town the mo<reg>s</reg>t con-
      <lb/><reg>s</reg>iderable in the Province of Tucuman,
      <lb/>as well for its Riches and Commodities,
      <lb/>as for the Number of its Inhabitants,
      <lb/>which are counted to be at lea<reg>s</reg>t 5 or
      <lb/>600 Families, be<reg>s</reg>ides Slaves who are
      <lb/>three times the number. But the gene
      <lb/>-rality of 'em of all degrees have no other
      <lb/>Arms but a Sword and Poignard, and
      <lb/>are very indifferent Souldiers, the Air
      <lb/>of the Country, and the Plenty they
      <lb/>enjoy, rendring them Lazy and Cow-
      <lb/>ardly.
   </p>
</div>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>